Welcome to week six, day three.
6주 차, 3일 차예요
Today is going to be a day that you will either love or you will hate, depending on your particular
오늘은 여러분의 선호도에 따라 호불호가 갈리는 날이 될 겁니다 하지만
preference, but I'm sure there's going to be no middle ground.
중간은 없을 거예요
It's either going to be a great day or a miserable day, depending on whether you like or are interested
멋진 하루가 되거나 끔찍한 하루가 될 겁니다 전통적인 머신 러닝에
in traditional machine learning, because today we're going to take a step back in time and look at
관심 있느냐에 따라서요 오늘은 과거로 한 걸음 돌아가 기본적인 머신
some foundational machine learning and get some practical examples of how things used to be.
러닝을 살펴보고 과거 어떻게 작동했는지 실질적인 예시를 볼 테니까요
So with that intro, and it's only for one day, I'm sure you can put up with it, even if it is something
그런 소개를 하루만 하면 참을 수 있을 거예요 아주 불쾌한 소개라도요 Put
that you find very unsavory.
it's go!
Well, as a quick reminder, what you can already do is work with frontier models, building AI assistants
다시 한번 말씀드리면 이미 여러분이 할 수 있는 건 개척 모델과 함께 작업하는 겁니다 도구를 이용한 인공지능
with tools, and with open source models like hugging face with pipelines and tokenizers and models.
조수 만들기 파이프라인, 토큰라이저 모델로 얼굴 안기 같은 오픈 소스 모델로요
You can use long chain to build a complete Rag pipeline.
긴 체인을 이용해 래그 파이프라인을 만들 수 있죠
And in fact, as you saw, it's actually quite, quite perfectly possible at least to do it without
사실, 보셨다시피 긴 체인 없이도 충분히 할 수
long chain as well.
있어요
It's just quicker if you use line chain, but you know that there's not anything particularly magic
라인 체인을 쓰면 더 빠르지만 헝겊은 특별한 마법이
about rag.
없어요
And then we've talked about a five step strategy to solve commercial problems.
그리고 상업적 문제를 해결하는 5단계 전략을 얘기했죠
And we've got really, really deep with data.
데이터도 아주 심오하고요
I hope it wasn't too deep.
상처가 깊지 않아야 할 텐데요
Hopefully you've survived the experience.
살아남았길 바라요
We did a lot of work with data.
데이터로 많은 작업을 했어요
We saw lots of charts.
차트를 많이 봤어요
You hopefully by now are very familiar with the item class and the item loader more than than perhaps
지금쯤이면 아이템 클래스와 아이템 로더에 익숙해졌을 겁니다 여러분이 의도했던
you'd ever intended to be.
것보다요
But at this point we know our data back to front.
하지만 이 시점에선 데이터를 처음부터 다 알아요
So today we talk about baselines.
오늘은 기준점에 대해 얘기할 거예요
I'm going to talk about what a baseline model is and why it's so important.
기준 모델이 무엇인지 왜 중요한지 말씀드리겠어요
And then we are going to at least I'm going to have an absolute blast playing with some baseline models
그런 다음 적어도 저는 기본 모델을 가지고 신나게 놀 겁니다 전통적인 머신
and exploring more traditional machine learning to see how good we can do without using all this fancy
러닝을 연구해 이런 화려한 LM 같은 걸 쓰지 않고도 얼마나 잘 만들어지는지
schmancy LM stuff.
볼 거예요
Um, before, uh, tomorrow, we turn to the frontier.
내일이 오기 전에 개척지로 향할 거예요
So without further ado, let's talk a bit about a baseline.
비트코인 기준에 대해 얘기해 보죠
So it's mostly common sense stuff that if you're looking to tackle a problem you start simple.
상식적인 문제지만 문제를 해결하려면 단순하게 시작해야죠
But in particular it's it's something which is fundamentally important in the world of data science
특히 데이터 과학의 세계에서 근본적으로 중요한 부분입니다 두 가지
for really a couple of reasons.
이유가 있어요
The obvious one is that it gives us a sort of yardstick, which we can use to measure progress against.
확실한 건 일종의 잣대를 제공한다는 거예요 진보를 측정할 때 사용할 수 있죠
If we start with something simple and traditional, then we know we're using, uh, sophisticated deep
단순하고 전통적인 것부터 시작하면 정교한 심층 신경망을 제대로 사용한다는 걸
neural networks properly.
알 수 있죠
When we see the needle moving and we see ourselves achieving far greater heights without that baseline,
바늘이 움직이고 기준선 없이 훨씬 더 높은 곳에 도달하는 걸 볼 때 알 수
we just don't know whether we're getting fabulous results or whether we're just making small steps in
없어요 멋진 결과를 얻는 건지 아니면 좋지 않은 방향으로 작은 발걸음을
a unpleasant direction.
내딛는 건지요
So obviously it gives us that yardstick.
이게 그 잣대를 제공하죠
Uh, but there's another thing, too, which is that llms are not always the right solutions.
하지만 다른 문제도 있어요 llm이 항상 옳은 해결책은 아니에요
In fact, in the specific business problem we're setting out to solve around, uh, around predicting
사실 저희가 해결하고자 하는 특정 사업상의 문제는 제품 가격 예측
prices of products.
문제인데요
It's not immediately obvious at all that llms are the right solution because typically, as I said before,
llms가 올바른 솔루션인지는 잘 알 수 없습니다 왜냐하면 일반적으로
generating a price, a number from a description seems like it's more traditional NLP and linear regression,
앞서 말했듯이 설명에서 가격과 숫자를 생성하는 것은 더 전통적인 NLP와 선형 회귀처럼 보이기 때문입니다
so it feels like it belongs in the field of machine learning.
머신 러닝 분야에 속한 것처럼 느껴지죠
A traditional machine learning.
전통적인 머신 러닝이죠
Um, and that makes it even more important to build a baseline, because for all we know, we'll do
그래서 기준점을 만드는 게 더 중요해요 기준점을 만든 다음에
that and then we'll try out frontier models and they won't do any better.
개척 시대 모델을 써 봐도 더 나을 게 없으니까요
So it's obvious stuff, but it explains why we do this.
뻔한 거지만 왜 이걸 하는지 설명해주죠
So what models are we going to be playing with today.
오늘은 어떤 모델을 가지고 놀까요?
And it's only one day.
하루면 돼요
It's only one time that we're going to spend doing this.
딱 한 번 하는 거잖아요
And you know, it's really worth it if you're already super familiar with these models.
이런 모델에 이미 아주 익숙하다면 그럴 가치가 있어요
And it's just going to be an interesting quick experiment with our particular commercial problem if
우리의 상업적 문제에 대한 흥미롭고 간단한 실험이 될 겁니다 처음
you're new to them, I'm not going to go into tons of detail on them, but it will give you a good sense
보시는 분들을 위해 자세하게 설명하진 않겠지만 어떤 관점인지
of the perspective.
잘 아실 거예요
Um, so the first thing we're going to do is we're going to take our business problem.
가장 먼저 할 일은 사업상의 문제를 해결하는 거예요
We're going to do something that's very old school.
아주 옛날 방식으로 할 거예요
We're going to do what they call feature engineering.
기능 엔지니어링이라고 부르는 걸 할 거예요
When we understand the data and we say, okay, what do we think are going to be some of the important
데이터를 이해하고 가격에 영향을 줄 수 있는 중요한 요인이
factors which are likely to affect the price?
무엇인지 생각해 보는 거죠
And we try and come up with these things that we will call features.
그리고 기능이라 부르는 것들을 생각해내려고 노력하죠
And we'll come up with some pretty obvious features, like how how do they rank in Amazon's best seller
그리고 몇 가지 특징을 생각해 낼 거예요 아마존 베스트셀러 순위에 어떻게 올랐는지
rank, that kind of thing.
그런 거요
And we will then try and see whether some linear combination of these features does a good job of predicting
그리고 이 세 가지 요소의 직선적 조합이 가격을 예측하는 데 도움이 되는지
the price or not.
볼 거예요
And that is often the place where you start when you're dealing with a machine learning model.
머신 러닝 모델을 다룰 때는 종종 거기서부터 시작하죠
We're then going to do something called Bag of Words, which is one of the first our first forays into
그리고 낱말 봉지라는 걸 할 거예요 자연 언어 처리를 처음 시도한
natural language processing.
것 중 하나죠
NLP Bag of Words is a particularly simplistic approach, where you quite literally count up the number
NLP 단어 주머니는 특히 단순한 접근법입니다 말 그대로 단어 수를
of words and you build yourself a little vector that consists of just how many times does each particular
세고 작은 벡터를 만드는 거죠 이 설명에서 각각의 단어가 몇 번 기능하는지
word feature in this description?
확인하는 거예요
So if you have a word, you one doesn't include what are known as stop words, which are words like
단어가 있다면 정지 단어는 포함하지 않습니다. 이런 단어는
the which, which aren't going to make much difference to anything.
어떤 것과도 크게 다르지 않아요.
But if there's a word like Intel, uh, which may indicate that it's a laptop or a computer that would
하지만 인텔 같은 단어가 특정 값을 가진 노트북이나 컴퓨터를 뜻한다면
have a certain value, Intel might be one of the words in our vocab.
인텔이 우리 단어 중 하나가 될 거예요
And depending on whether that appears or not or if it does, how many times it appears that will affect
그게 나타나느냐에 따라 혹은 나타난다면 그 장소에 얼마나 많이 나타나느냐에
that location.
따라 달라져요
Uh, in our in in this bag of words, this list of counts of words in each product.
각 제품에 들어간 단어 목록이 들어 있어요
And then we're going to take that bag of words and again see if there's some linear combination of these
그런 다음 단어 봉지를 가져다가 이 다양한 단어들의 선형 조합이
different words that, when combined together predicts the price of a product.
있는지 보겠습니다 그걸 다 합쳤을 때 제품 가격을 예측하죠
We then going to use something called word two vec, which I mentioned some time ago, which was one
그리고 워드 2 벡이라는 걸 사용할 겁니다 아까도 언급했지만
of the first real sort of, uh, neural network, um, Encoding algorithms that could produce a vector
최초의 실제 신경망 중 하나로 알고리즘을 인코딩하는 거죠 단어보다 더 영리한 방식으로
in a way that is rather smarter than a bag of words.
벡터를 생성할 수 있어요
And we'll first use that with linear regression.
그걸 먼저 선형 회귀와 함께 사용할 거예요
And then we're going to use that with random forests, which is a more sophisticated technique that
그다음 무작위 포레스트에 사용할 겁니다 좀 더 복잡한 기술이죠 그때 말씀드릴게요
But it involves taking random chunks of your data and your features in the form of bits of vectors,
하지만 벡터 비트 형태로 데이터와 기능을 무작위로 취하고 벡터 비트가 벡터인지
and seeing whether and then creating an ensemble, a series of models that combines averages across
아닌지를 확인한 후 이런 샘플 여러 개를 합친 일련의 모델로 앙상블을 생성하는
many of these little samples.
걸 포함하죠
And then we're going to have something called support vector regression, a type of support vector machines,
그리고 벡터 회귀 지원이라는 것이 있습니다 벡터 머신의 지원 유형으로 다른
which is another technique, a specific way of trying to separate out your data into different groups.
기술입니다 데이터를 여러 그룹으로 분리하는 방법이죠
So we will try these different techniques.
다양한 기술을 시도해 볼 거예요
We will see which one does best and see how that fares in solving our problem of predicting the price
어느 제품이 가장 잘 팔리고 제품 설명만 보고 가격을 예측하는 문제를
of a product based only on its description.
해결할 수 있을지 지켜보죠
With that, let's go to JupyterLab.
그럼 주피터랩으로 가보죠